[Music]
Stanford
University I gather you people had a lot
of fun with
entanglement it's a good subject I mean
it's really is absolutely the heart of
quantum
mechanics but of
course yeah I mean I would say up till
now we have really studied the
foundations of quantum mechanics in very
very simple systems and the foundations
have been laid out they've been exposed
you know what they are and really the
only thing left to do now is to study
some
examples question yeah so In classical
mechanics we started with a very small
number of empirical observations by
Newton and sort of everything else was
obtained by mathematics sort of more or
less more or less so what's the
equivalent in the case of quantum
mechanics what are the sort of basic
Atomic empirical observations you mean
historically well the minimal set that
you need
well I would say the minimum set is what
we
described when we talked about an
apparatus which you could
rotate a
spin and um a window in the apparatus
that was zero and one that's logically
the simplest thing you can do it's of
course not the way quantum mechanics was
discovered um but just as
analyzing the experimental data that you
would get by taking an electron or spin
orienting your uh your detector pressing
the M button the measure button and
getting a uh one or minus one on the
screen doing this over and over and over
again accumulating
statistics uh is the um is the simplest
thing you can do and you have to do that
for each physical property like momentum
like Spin and so on
yes right m a quick question on the on
the system you described with the
singlet and the triplet and the photon
going off you said if you capture the
photon quickly and reflect it back is
that simply because you only have a
system with just a singlet and the
triplet or can any other Photon also
cause dising entanglement no that's a
good question
well
um you don't have a photon out there you
have a photon or you don't have a photon
the radiation field itself is not in a
state of positive uh you know whether
whether or not you have a photon out
there could also be thought of as a zero
or
one the radiation State itself the
radiation system itself could be modeled
by having another degree of
freedom and the other degree of Freedom
could also have a Zer or one Z would
mean no Photon present one would mean a
photon present okay
so what happens let's suppose we start
with a singlet and the
triplet superposed in this way
with no
photons all right so to express the fact
that there are no photons we have to put
another degree of freedom in here and we
have to say this is a tensor
product with a state of the radiation
field which has no
photons that's the way and keep in mind
this here represents the two electrons
either in the singlet State or the
triplet State and this represents the
state of the um of the radiation field
now if you wait for a little
while and while the electrons are
entangled here they are not entangled
with the radiation field this is a
simple product of a vacuum of photons no
photons and a particular state of the
uh of the electron pair in fact I said
this was entangled this is not entang
Tangled this combination was just up
down all right now you let it evolve for
a while what happens is the
singlet stays the
singlet and it does not AIT a
photon but the triplet what happens to
it it becomes the
singlet and emits a photon
so what happens to the state it is
evolves into the linear combination of
singlet times no Photon and one Photon
in other words it's a singlet electron
it's a singlet state of the electron
pair but a linear
superposition Quantum linear
superposition of no Photon and one
Photon that seems a little bit strange
but it's an important idea that you can
not only superpose states of a particle
you can superpose the number of
particles no particle and one particle
can be Quantum any two states can be
superposed so the state of a system of
the vacuum empty
space that's a state with no
photons a state with one photon is a
state with one Photon and you can add
them that's what's Happening Here you
would eventually come to the state which
is
singlet
times no
Photon plus one
Photon this state
now is it entangled between the are the
electrons entangled with the radiation
field no because it's pure product but
are the electrons entangled with each
other yeah because it's singlet state
only the singlet State appears here and
the singlet state is an entangled state
so the electrons are entangled with each
other but they're not entangled with the
radiation field on the other hand the
radiation field is left in a
superposition of states of having a
photon and not having a photon uh so
what do we start
with we started with a
unentangled state of the electrons
totally unentangled with the radiation
field I say this is unentangled with the
electrons because that's what we started
with UD UD and no Photon so we started
with unentangled completely everything
unentangled waited for a photon to be
emitted when the photon was emitted the
sing the triplet state became the
singlet state but it emitted a photon
and the result was an entangled state of
the electrons
but unentangled with the with the
radiation field
okay it's pretty tricky set of ideas you
haven't brought anything externally at
like a magnetic field so that what's
causing uh no no no no no no in order to
um no there's no nothing external here
so what causes the the triplet to emit
the photon is interaction with the other
electron which is why they right
right the interaction between the two
electrons roughly speaking each electron
is in the magnetic field of another
electron but what they want to do is
maximum anti-align or better yet they
want to minimize or make maximally
negative the value of sigma.
to that's the so they emit a photon to
do that
all right the last time we started to
move on
to the problem of particle
motion for get particle
spin of course real particles may have
both position and
spin but let's concentrate for today on
um
questions relating to the position of
particles the simplest example we can
think of is a particle moving on a
one-dimensional axis
X there it
is um before we study that I wanted to
do a little mathematical interlude it'll
take uh at most 10 minutes maybe
less having to do with Foria analysis
Foria transform
and its relationship to uh to the direct
Delta function so let's take a
Blackboard and do some mathematics on
it
okay the function e to the IX let's take
P to be a number P is a number now it's
not a variable e to the
IX that's a combination of s and cosine
functions and therefore it has a WAV
like character and we call it a plain
wave we call it a plain wave uh just the
simple waves cosiness and signs
combination of cosine p.x and sin I sin
p.x and you can think of it as a wave of
course it's not move just writing e to
the ipx doesn't give it any time
dependent so it doesn't move but it's
wav
like okay um a very wide class of
functions and certainly all the
functions we will be interested in can
be written as sums of plain waves or
integrals better yet integrals of plain
waves and decomposing a function in this
case a function of X let's call it s of
X decomposing it into plain waves is
called Foria analysis now most of you
know that in fact most of you or some of
you in any case know about Foria
analysis but we're going to spell it out
now
every function that we will be
interested
in in fact it's probably true that that
excludes almost all
functions but we also exclude almost all
functions when we say that they're
continuous when we say that they're
differentiable when we say uh uh that we
can express them in any meaningful
sensible form we exclude almost all
functions but if we take our functions
to be reasonable continuous Reon and I
won't try to be very very precise uh
continuous and um not to blow up at
Infinity in other words to uh to fall to
zero at minus infinity at plus infinity
almost all functions or all functions we
will be interested in uh can
be expanded in waves in this way now
expanded means they can be written as
integrals
over
P what is p p tells you how fast the
wave
oscillates this is some moderate value
of P if I increase P I create a wave
with a very short
wavelength decrease P I'm talking about
a wave with a very long
wavelength so this is just saying we
can decompose function into waves of
different
wavelengths each wavelength has an
amplitude an amount of that wave that's
in there and we'll call that s twidle of
p time e to the I
PX s twiddle of p
is just the
amplitude that uh the wave
of type P has strength s of p in the
function s of X okay 4a's
theorem is a theorem which tells you how
to
reconstruct side TT of P I'm going to
just for definition this is purely for
definition I'm going to put a one over
sare root of 2 pi
here that's that's a
convention we could have absorbed it
into s twiddle of p s TD is complex s
twiddle typically is complex and so will
s of X be complex that's a good question
both of them I intend for the moment to
be complex now it may happen that one of
these is real and the other one is
complex that can happen but at the
moment we're just interested in
arbitrary complex functions that's right
all right the question is how do you
reconstruct s tdle of P from s of X and
I'm going to leave it as something you
can look up if you don't know it it's
the basic theorem of Foria
analysis that s tdle of
p and notice that s of X is an integral
over
p s twidle of p is going to be an
integral over
X DX over < TK 2
pi
times s of x
and the natural thing would be to write
here e to the IX but it's not it's e to
the minus
IX uh 2 pi thank
you that's the basic theorem of Foria
analysis that if s of X is the Foria
transform of s twidle of
P defined in this way then s twidle of P
is a forer transform of s of X very much
the same pattern except that you put an
e to the minus I PX
there we will need that
theorem so if you don't know that
theorem it's a very important uh theorem
in quantum
mechanics and it expresses a kind of
reciprocal relationship between X and
P which of course ultimately are going
to be position and
momentum okay that's that's one little
mathematical uh interlude that uh that
we will need the other has to do with
the Delta
function and then we're going to combine
them
together for a mathematician the
definition we have a we have a a
intuitive definition of a Delta function
it's a high narrow function that's so
narrow that its width is essentially
zero and so high that the area under it
is one okay we can call that a
representation of the Delta
function um a definition of the Delta
function of course the Delta function is
not a real function it's infinite
somewhere but uh you know that
that's uh that's an anal attitude about
the Delta
function it took years from physicists
incidentally to convince mathematicians
that Delta functions were okay
mathematicians didn't like them for a
very good reason their functions they
can't you can't Square them though
they're just there if you square them
they're still zero everywhere except at
the same point but instead of having a
height uh big enough to make the area
one they have a height which is the
square of that and so they themselves
are not the are worse
objects but they got over it I mean they
got over it and uh and I'm told Now by
some of my mathematician friends that
it's okay to write a Delta
function okay properties of the Delta
function the first thing in the way a
mathematician would think about it is
it's an operation that you can do on a
function in particular you can
integrate any function of X any
reasonable function of X with the Delta
function Delta of x - x
Prime oh no let's go a step no no no
let's uh let's even go uh let's not even
do that
yet let's take Delta of x - x Prime * F
ofx first property of the Delta function
is that this is equal
to f of x
Prime Time Delta of x - x
Prime why would that be true that's
certainly wouldn't be true for a general
function uh Delta the reason it's true
is because Delta is only nonzero when X
is equal to X Prime so it's no big deal
Delta of x - x Prime is only non zero
when xal X Prime and therefore it
doesn't matter whether you put X or X
Prime when multiplying it by a function
so that that's property number
one now property number two that pretty
much follows from that
no not yet property one next property
two integral of Delta of x - x
Prime is always equal to 1 that's just
the statement that the area under this
bump is equal to one and it doesn't
matter where you put it you put it over
here or you put it over here or you put
it over here the area is always equal to
one and so the integral of Delta of x -
x Prime let's say from minus infinity to
Infinity is always equal to
1 and the last property which follows
from these
two is that the
integral the integral of Delta of x - x
Prime f ofx
is equal to F ofx
Prime now you see it in two ways one is
that you can say look the Delta function
is only non zero when X is equal to X
Prime and so it picks out the value X
Prime in F ofx or you can just say use
property where is it property number one
to rewrite this in the form f of x
Prime integral Delta of x x - x
Prime
DX why am I allowed to bring the F ofx
Prime on the
outside because it doesn't depend on X
it's just X Prime itself is a constant h
x Prime itself is a constant is a fixed
value from the point of view of uh yeah
that's right so I that's right so I just
bring it on the outside and then I say
the integral under the Delta function is
one and so I just get F ofx
Prime all right so those are
the obvious properties of the Delta
function which you might use to atiz
what a Delta function
is okay now I'm going to prove a
theorem which is provides a
representation of the Delta function an
important representation of the Delta
function uh let's uh I think we can
erase this for the moment
then I want to eras that I probably
didn't
integral f of x Delta of x - x Prime is
equal to f of x Prime now this actually
is a sufficient definition of the Delta
function this is the way the
mathematicians Define it as an operation
that you do on a function it gives the
value of the function at some
point and this is enough to Define um uh
uh the Delta function if it's not enough
to define the Delta function if there's
only one function f if this is true for
every function f there's only one
function only
one Delta here that will fill that uh
property okay so this can be taken as
the defining function if for all F this
is true then this is the Delta
function what's that yeah DX DX good
DX okay now what I want to do is I want
to take the two top
equations and put them together here's
what I'm going to do I'm going to write
that s of X is equal to this thing but
then I'm going to plug in for this
thing the second equation and reexpress
S of X Back In terms of the function s
of X itself and let's see what we
get either we'll get something
completely trivially stupid or we will
learn something and the fact is we will
learn something so let's take s of X and
write it s of
X is equal I'm just going to write now
integral DP over sare < TK of 2 pi e to
the
IX and now I'm going to shove in the
second equation
for S twiddle of p and that is let's put
a bracket around
it DX
integral let's let's
um yeah hold on a
second
um let's call a s of X Prime and to make
a s of X Prime all we have to do is put
a prime
here uh I've just changed the name of
the variable on the left side and to do
so of course I have to change the name
of the variable on the right hand side
all right I don't want to confuse x and
x Prime all right now the second
equation for S twiddle of P that I can
leave as it is and just write that it's
integral DX over < TK 2
pi s of
x e to the minus I PX
so I've just plugged in side twiddle of
P now
integrals are generally insensitive to
which order you do the integrals is
particularly if they're Integrations
from minus infinity to Infinity as they
are here both of
them if they're well defined and they
converge in everything
then it doesn't matter which order you
do the Integrations so let's start let's
isolate some things let's put here
integral DP over 2
pi oh over 2 pi we now have a single
factor of 2
pi one coming from here one coming from
here let's isolate e to the i p x Prime
minus X from
here we have e to the I PX Prime
e to Theus I PX that's e to the i p x -
x
Prime uh and
then we still haven't written down s of
X so let's write down s of
X and now interchange the order of
integration of X and P and write this as
integral
DX integral DX that's equal to S of X
Prime so look what we have we have a
relationship between s of X and S of X
Prime we have a way of writing s of X
Prime in terms of s of X but what is it
but look what stands
here take this whole thing
here this is an integral over P it's
true but all it is is some function of X
Prime minus X right let's give it a name
let's call it the capital Delta function
let's call this the capital Delta
function and write this
DX Capital Delta of X Prime -
x this whole mess here including the 2
pi and everything
else after integration over P Time s of
x equals s of X
Prime what does it tell you about this
Capital Delta
function it's just a good old Delta
function it's just a good old direct
Delta function so we've proved an
interesting relationship and one that is
at the heart
of many many things in quantum
[Music]
mechanics here it is the integral
DP over
pi e to the i p of x - x
Prime is equal to Delta of x - x
Prime in other words a kind of screwball
way of writing the Delta function by
itself expressing it as a Foria
transform or a sum of plain
waves we can also
write this in we can write we're not
writing the same thing I'm writing a
different thing but just by
interchanging X and
P by interchanging X and P I can write
another equation DX over 2
pi e to the
i x of P minus P Prime equals Delta of P
minus P Prime this is
these two are
identical these two are identical I've
just changed the name of x to p and p to
X right if this equation is true this
equation is true because they're exactly
the same equation except that I've
interchanged the name x with p and p
with
X all right so this is a uh this is an
important as I said
um fact about Delta functions
these are the basic mathematical facts
that we
need this here is not important we've
got the we've got it on the Blackboard
over
there oh if you don't like the way I got
the second one from the first one by
just interchanging p and X you can go
back to these equations and instead of
eliminating s twiddle of
P
eliminate s of X by substituting in s of
x from here and and you'll get uh you
know you'll just you just interchange p
and
X good all right so now we have what we
need yeah on on the left hand side
underneath the board that you just
brought down yeah you you wrote x
primeus x but then on the right you X
does that imply a actually it doesn't
matter it's a good question it doesn't
matter and the reason is Delta of x - x
Prime is unchanged if you interchange X
x and x Prime it's a symmetric function
of its argument if you interchange Delta
of x - x Prime is the same as Delta of X
Prime minus X so uh you can check that
so the answer is it doesn't matter
um whether but you're probably right
probably if I did the derivation um
systematically I might have gotten X
Prime minus X here but then the end it
doesn't
matter okay so let's uh let's add
this equation over
here integral
DP over 2 pi e to the i p either x - x
prime or X Prime - x doesn't matter is
equal to Delta of x - x
Prime and integral DX over 2
pi e to the
i p minus P Prime * x * X
is equal to Delta of P minus P
Prime all right now let's come back to
the world of physics the world of
quantum mechanics a particle on a
line if we were doing classical
physics we would describe the particle
on the line
the state of a particle on the line by a
point in Phase
space and phas Bas consists of a value
of x and a value of
P one of each for a one-dimensional
particle just one uh 1 x and 1
P what about quantum mechanics how do we
describe the state of a quantum
mechanical particle well you can try to
make some guesses um
what not how do you describe the state
but what can how do we describe an
orthonormal basis of states that always
is the question give me when you start a
new system you ask
what defines the space of states and one
way of defining the space of states is
to provide an orthogonal normalized
basis of states and all states then are
linear superpositions of that basis all
right there are various possibilities
you might you might wonder maybe uh
the States can be represented by the
position of a
particle X you might think maybe that
can be represented by the momentum of a
particle or you might wonder might the
states be represented as a pair an X and
the
P this is large After All In classical
physics it takes an X and A P to
describe the position of the the um the
state of a particle what is it in
quantum mechanics in the answer is in
quantum mechanics that X and P are too
much
information in the same way that uh for
the spin knowing Sigma X and sigma y or
Sigma Z and sigma y or whatever is too
much information you can't know both of
them
simultaneously the same of course is
true in quantum mechanics it's actually
more familiar it's called of course the
Heisenberg uncertainty principle but you
can't know both so it's one or the other
classical physics a particle has an X
and A P in some sense in quantum
mechanics a particle has an X or a
meaning to say you don't try to describe
it by both you describe it by one or the
other and we'll we'll see what the
relationship is in a
moment so we suppose that there is an
igen Vector of an observable position
for every value of the observable
position this Vector represents um a
state in which the position of the
particle is definite and at position
X so it's an igen Vector of something
which we'll think of as an observable X
we'll we'll understand a little more
mathematically in a
moment and like any good basis the point
of a basis is to write any wave
function s or any state
Vector as a superposition a sum of the
basis
vectors since the basis vectors form a
continuous range of possibility
we write it as an integral
DX replacing the sum and then I Vector
x times something which depends on
X this is completely analogous to what
we've done in the past where we've taken
a arbitrary vector and expanded it in
terms of igen vectors of something and
these are the coefficients here and we
call these things the wave function we
call these things the wave function
uh and in fact they are given by the
inner product of the igen vector s igen
Vector x with the state s that is s of X
this is fully analogous to what we
studied in simpler systems wave function
is the projection of the state onto a
state of definite
X that's s of x
X and secondly s star of x * s of
X is the
probability that the particle be found
at position X now strictly speaking we
talked about it last time strictly
speaking you have to think of it as a
particle as a probability
density uh a probability per unit
X or probability per unit interval in x
but you know you know how to take that
into account all right so that's uh this
is the basic framework of quantum
mechanics just being repeated except for
a continuous variable the inner product
between two vectors x and x
Prime is zero unless xal X
Prime and if these were Contin if these
were standard discrete variables we
would say zero unless xal X Prime are
one if x equals x Prime we would write
chronica Delta x x Prime but uh X that's
not helpful for continuous variables for
continuous variables we write the Delta
function the Delta function the direct
Delta function it's the Continuum
analog of the chronica delta
we have bra vectors and K
vectors if a k Vector is described by a
s of x a bra Vector of course would be
described in a similar way in terms of s
star of X so
K's s of X wave functions
bras SAR of X usual thing nothing new
here finally the inner product not
finally but the inner product not
between x and x Prime but between two
arbitrary States let's call them
s and
fi each one of which can be
expanded by use of a wave
function f
is described by a wave function f
ofx the bra
vectori can you tell the difference
between my size and my f when I say
it yeah okay this is Greek fi this is
Greek
Pai but I can't I never say Pai I say
Sai I think the Greeks do also anybody
know
so is this really just a bunch of
sci-fi so must thought of that write
that down keep
that
good okay and this one is described by S
star of
X and if you expand them both
appropriately in igen vectors of X bra
vectors and K vectors and then use the
inner product rule here for the igen
vectors of X you will get of course that
the inner product is the integral
DX it follows by simply expanding SI
expanding
F and uh using this inner product here
but it's also hardly surprising it's the
same kind of formula that we would have
uh previously for this stre
systems and last but
uh question
uh so position and momentum is too much
information so we're asserting really
that it's just the position that gives
us a complete basis and pretty much
anything else is going to be too much
information not
just don't redundant yeah pretty much
anything else now now the only reason
I'm hesitating is because we could
imagine a particle moving in two
Dimensions right in that case it's not
clear yet whether we can know the x
coordinate of the position and the y
coordinate of momentum for example the
answer is you
can so
um but if our system was just a particle
in one dimension that's
it X
um right
so that's a good
point so does that mean that momentum
then can essentially be expanded can be
treated as a as a side say it again so
that essentally that means that momentum
can be treated as a side and hence
expand be expanded by an integral
involving X that right
yes four your transforms are four right
okay let's
um oh one last
thing the probability density is SAR s
not SAR F SAR s and if I integrate SAR s
with respect to X that would be the
inner product of s with
itself and that should be equal to one
on the basis that the uh total
probability should be one in other words
nothing new again uh physical States
should be normalized normalized so that
integral SI stari is equal to
one okay
now next last time we talked about some
observables the position and the
momentum so let's uh review a little bit
about
that let's invent an operator now
capital X here maybe I should uh how can
I indicate that it's a capital x um
let's put an extra line in that makes it
a capital x and therefore an operator as
opposed to just a number an igen
value this is the operator or the
observable which
whose igen values are the positions of
the particles the
observables okay the observable values
um let's talk about the action of s of
X when it hits a vector that's what
operators do they hit vectors and they
make new vectors all right I'm going to
tell you what the action is by telling
you how it behaves in terms of wave
functions instead of telling you how s
acts on an abstract Vector I'm going to
tell you what happens
when the operator
X hits a wave function wave functions
and state vectors can be thought of as
uh one being a representation of the
other when X hits s of
X what it does is just multiply s of X
by
X in other words it gives you another
function that's the nature of operators
they act on function functions to give
other functions they act on vectors to
give other vectors if uh if functions
are representations or uh constructions
which represent those vectors
then
uh whatever linear operators are they
should be such that they do something to
the wave function and this is what x
does to the wave function it simply
multiplies it by X it gives you a new
function which uh it's not the same
function it's a different
function but uh that's that's the nature
of it now let's prove
something let's prove that the igen
vectors and the igen values of this
operator are what we expect them to be
you of course do expect them to be
something you may not realize at this
moment that you expect them to be
something but as soon as I show you what
they are you will say oh yes we expected
that okay so what is likely to be the
igen vector
of capital x well it should be a state
it should be a state where the particle
is
localized at position
X right in particular let's uh let's
talk about the particle being localized
at point x
knot what would we expect the igen
vector to be it should be a function
which is zero everywhere except at X
notot right
that's uh that's what we would expect it
should be concentrated at X knot and so
let's try the function Delta of x - x x
is just a parameter here now it's a
function of X but it's the function of X
which represents the particle at
position X
notot and let's ask the question when
you operate with the operator X on this
wave function what do you get well the
answer is you just multiply it by Little
X
but now we go back to one of the
properties of the Delta
function namely that when you multiply
it by any function of X you can replace
it by a function of X
Prime so or in this case X
not this is also equal to x * Delta of x
-
x but what is this equation this is
exactly the equation for an igen Vector
of the and igen value of the operator X
the operator X hits the wave function
and gives a number times the same wave
function okay operator HS wave function
gives number times wave function it's
clear that this is an igen Vector of the
operator with igen value
xot all right so now we can make a list
of igen vectors of various uh various
observables we're starting off list igen
values and igen vectors the igen vector
associated with a particle localized at
point xnot that is
equal to the Delta function of x - x
exactly as you expected
right good
okay I'm sure you
did and that finishes up
x what about P what about momentum
again
momentum being an observable you can
observe it if it hits you in the side of
the head you feel
it you
recoil that is what momentum is it's uh
momentum means the same thing in quantum
mechanics as it does in classical
mechanics it's conserved and so if you
absorb something with some momentum you
uh you
recoil all right what is the momentum
operator the momentum operator and we
will the justification for this will
come a little
later uh we did talk about it but I want
to go back over it momentum is called
P the operator
momentum the operator momentum is equal
to there's no point beating around the
bush let's say what it's equal to it is
equal to minus I and I'm going to put in
some units
here later on we will set H bar equal to
one it's just a choice of units but for
the moment let's keep har bar there
times the derivative
operator D the thing I called D last
time or the operator
D last time we studied whether capital D
was Herm Mission or not and we found
that it was
not but if we multiplied it by I either
with a plus or minus sign it doesn't
matter uh if we uh multiply it by an I
then it becomes Herm Mission so we we we
worked that out last time if you
remember that little trick with the
integration by
parts uh we found that D was not her
Mission but uh I * D is all right so
this is the definition of the momentum
operator or it's a it's a bunch of
symbols so far but what is p do when it
acts on a wave function it just gives
minus
I time DCI by
DX so it is also an operator it's also
an operation it's an operator it's a
linear operator and it is a Herm Mission
linear operator p
so that's what it takes to qualify as an
observable in quantum
mechanics
um at this point since s is only a
function of one variable it doesn't
matter whether I use partial derivatives
or just ordinary derivatives D let's
call them ordinary derivatives d by
DX next question what is the igen
vectors of the momentum the igen vectors
of the momentum
satisfy p on S or minus I HR d s by
DX equal some igen
value some observable value or some
possible outcome of an experiment let's
call it
P Time
s this of course p is a number it's the
igen
value uh we can let's let's just
um if we get rid of the minus I here it
becomes a plus I on this side and we can
divide by H
bar all right so this is just the
equation for an exponential derivative
being proportional to the same
function uh and the solution for
S it's Unique apart from a
multiplicative constant
s this is the igen
vector uh as a function of
X and let's label it by P not all right
just to label the fact that it's the
igen vector for momentum P not it's a
function of X and what is it it's e to
the
i p x
question oh thank you over har
bar all right I'm just going to keep the
H bar around for about 10 more seconds I
just want to point out that this is a
WAV like thing this is a wavelike thing
it has signs and cosiness and it has a
wavelength the wavelength is the
distance that you have to move so that
the thing in the exponent changes by 2
pi in other words if we call the
wavelength Lambda p over HR time Lambda
equals 2 pi that's the definition of the
wavelength how far do you have to move
so that the SS and cosines return to
themselves or that the
wavelength is 2 pi
HR divided by P P being the momentum of
the
particle so here we see the first
example of the relationship between
momentum and
wavelength larger the momentum the
smaller the
wavelength of course we have not yet
Justified the choice of the terminology
momentum for this
thing but uh we can keep in mind that
later on we're going to want to come
back and see that this P really does
behave like
momentum uh but so far it's just an
abstract observ able we don't know what
it means yet okay so here we are Lambda
is equal to this and now that I have
demonstrated that let's get rid of har
bar because I will forget about it
anyway let's get rid of har bar get rid
of this formula here and say this is the
uh now it's not clear yet that I've
normalized this correctly it's not clear
yet that this is normalized to
one uh let's take the inner product
between two momentum States all right
this is this here is a representation of
the momentum State P
not or let's just call it P let's just
call it P get rid of the notot not
serving any real purpose here
P but think of p uh just
P let's take the inner product of two
momentum States P Prime and
P where's our formula for inner products
here it is right over
here uh no here it is over
here one SAR and one
fi so that means the inner product is
the
integral
of e to the minus i p Prime X that's the
wave function of P prime or the a
complex conjugate of it and then the
wave function
for uh e to the
I PX
DX or
equivalently integral e to the i p minus
P
Prime X
DX now if we've done things right since
p is supposed to be a observable a Herm
Mission operator and and the igen
vectors of Herm Mission operators should
be
orthogonal then this should be zero if p
is not equal to P
Prime it's pretty clear that it is zero
if z p is not equal to P Prime and for
the following
reason um the real and imaginary parts
of e to the i p minus P Prime X are
cosiness and
signs if p is not equal to P Prime these
are Co cosin and
SS of P minus P Prime X cosiness and
signs are as positive as they are
negative if you integrate them over a
large interval you'll get zero as long
as you pick up an integer number of
wavelengths and that's uh that's
important here so as long as p is not
equal to P Prime this integral just
oscillates itself to
zero
okay uh equally positive and equally
negative for both real and imaginary
parts so it is true P Prime is not equal
to sorry P the inner product is equal to
zero if p is not equal to P Prime what
about if p is equal to P
Prime this is integral from minus
infinity to
Infinity without looking at the other
Blackboard uh what what can we say about
this for p not for p equal to P
Prime it's going to be infinite right
the integral of one integrated over all
space is infinite so in fact it's sort
of looking it's smelling like it is the
Delta
function it's smelling like it is the
Delta function infinite when p is equal
to P Prime and zero otherwise it's a
good thing but we don't know what the
actual numerical coefficient is but yes
we do up here we have
uh integral where was uh that's this one
over here integral
DX over 2
pi is Delta of P minus P Prime the
upshot of
this is just that in order for this to
be normalized so it's inner product is a
real Delta function you have to dis
divide by the square root of two yeah
square root of 2 pi big
deal square root of 2 pi this this is
the wave function for a particle of
momentum
uh
here a particle of momentum P we now
know what the wave functions of
particles of momentum P
are question yeah um when you were
talking about uh two different p and p
Prime you talked about taking the
integral from minus infinity to Infinity
of some oscillating function and and you
said this is zero and I'm just trying to
think in my head normally when you do an
integral you how do you justify that
zero yeah I can see it's sort of average
zero but I'm not really sure how to
justify it yeah I knew somebody was
going to
ask yeah the answer is that you really
justify it by starting with a theory on
a finite
interval you're asking I think questions
about convergence of the integral
integral doesn't really
converge so you really have to go back
to some earlier starting point which had
I start if I were teaching quantum
mechanics in a graduate class or
something I would have
started by thinking of a theory on a
finite interval or even better on a
finite periodic interval worked it out
and then taken carefully the limit as
you let things get the go to
infinity and then everything could be
justified with
rigor we don't have the time and so I um
I don't do
that but of course about the transform
itself right yeah it's not really fun to
mechanics because I was just thinking
about the it's a fact about the forer
transform but I did
cheat I did cheat at some point I
interchanged an X integration with a p
integration and one of those
Integrations didn't converge I did
basically the same cheat that I did here
um but but you know I I wouldn't cheat
you if I didn't know that the steps can
be filled in and if I didn't know that
if you go and find yourself a book on
for year transforms you won't be able to
fill the steps in yourself so uh I
haven't really cheated what I've done
was just a little bit of a short uh
shortcut all right now we've talked
about the wave functions of particles
with momentum P but now I want to talk
about a different concept the wave
function in the momentum basis so far
all of these wave functions have been
thought of as functions of x p here is
just a parameter it's uh the momentum of
the particle
but the wave function is a function of X
oh incidentally notice something
important notice something important the
wave functions of particles with
definite momentum oscillate endlessly
forever and ever and they're absolutely
unlocalized they're as delocalized as
they can be in particular SAR s of X is
uniformly spread out over the entire
real axis in most sense is the
position well defined it's as uncertain
as it could be on the other hand the
momentum is very precise this is an igen
Vector of the momentum operator If This
Were the wave function of a particle and
you measured its momentum it would be P
if you measured its position it would be
random all over the axis okay very much
well much worse then but very much like
the sigma X and the sigma Z
representations uh where one may be
definite and at the cost of the other
one being as indefinite as possible in
that case it's just one and minus
one here it's much
worse so when a particle is uh
localized in momentum it's completely
delocalized in
position we want to be able to say we
want to I would like to do the
reciprocal thing also I'd like to go in
the other direction for that what we
want to do is construct a notion called
the momentum space wave function the
momentum space wave function is related
to the probability amplitude for finding
different momenta so let's see if we can
construct that for that uh I think we're
finished over here
all
right we defined in general we Define a
wave function by taking the state vector
and projecting it onto igen vectors of
various observables and that gives us
the wave function in the basis
associated with that with that
observable uh if I project it
onto an igen state of X that gives me
the wave function side of x if
instead I project it onto a state of
definite momentum that gives me
something that I can call the wave
function in the momentum
basis okay it's not a function of X so
it doesn't look like a wave in
space doesn't look like a wave in space
but it's called The Wave fun and it's a
function of
momentum what is it let's give it a name
let's call it s twiddle of
P just to I I use the twiddle notation
just to to um remind you that it's a
different thing a different different
animal from the uh from the xwave
function how do we calculate this let's
suppose we know the X representation of
the of the state Vector s of X how do we
calculate this well we take the inner
product of the state Vector
s with the vector P but we know what
that is that's the integral
DX I think I've lost it no I I don't
mean yeah only the only the equ only the
equation what was it
sci-fi equals
integral uh SAR of x
Pi
ofx
DX okay so I want the inner product
between P well I know the wave function
of p in the position basis it's just
what is it it's e to the minus I
PX over the < TK of 2 pi if I remember
right that's what we
uh that's what we wrote down for S Sub P
of x that's this guy over here and then
we have to multiply that by S of
X and
integrate but that's exactly equal to
side twiddle of p uh with the same
notation that I used for Foria
transforms in other words the momentum
State wave function s twidle of p is
exactly the Foria transform
of the position space wave function
that's the
upshot momentum and position are related
in the same way that ordinary variables
positions and uh forer variables are
related okay so here we have let's just
call a side ttle of
p and if you know what this says is if
you know the wave function and the
position basis you know everything
that's enough in fact you can recover
the wave function in the momentum basis
and also the probability to find the
particle with different momenta after
all what is the pro uh I've abused the
notation this shouldn't be a capital S
here this should be a small s it's a
wave
function and of course the
probability to measure a given value of
momentum is just
s twiddle star of P
Time s tdle of P so what do you
do and some way or another you know what
the wave function of a particle is s of
X but you're not interested in measuring
X you're interested in measuring P how
do you determine the various
probabilities for measuring different P
you take that xwave function you subject
it to fora transform you find
the for your transform of it and its
square is the probability for different
momentum this is extremely similar to
going from the sigma Z basis to the
sigma X
basis go through it and see if you can
uh find the similarities between the
two so if you wanted to take a position
operator in the momentum space it would
be I parti
parti right
remember
P was equal to minus i d by
DX and you apply this to a position
space wave function you apply it to a
position space wave function to find out
how it
acts X
not quite
parallel not minus i d by DP but plus I
D by
DP the minus sign difference has a great
deal to do with this minus sign here but
you can work it
out I um this is the first time that
I've seen an explanation for a
Heisenberg pair
of position versus momentum and I assume
that a similar relationship would apply
to other Heisenberg pairs like time and
energy time and energy is a funny one
time is not usually regarded as an
operator in quantum mechanics it's not
usually regarded although you could
um you know you do measure time you look
at your watch the hand of your watch
isn't
observable and so in that sense uh clock
readings can be thought of as
observables there's something a little
bit funny about them and I don't want to
get into it now but um
but usually in quantum mechanics time is
just considered the parameter by which
states evolve but it is true if you have
a clock for
example and uh you're interested in
making that uh making an
extremely um accurate observation of the
clock it will be at the cost of um a
lack of uh Precision in the energy of
the clock so yeah it is what heberg
pairs are there that that I might not be
aware of electric and magnetic field
just uh almost anything you can think of
uh will have a uh a conjugate variable
electric and magnetic field
um uh
what's that temperature and pressure no
temperature and pressure are statistical
mechanical variables they're not quantum
mechanical variables
uh what's that angular
momentum yeah well okay the angular
momentum and
angle if an angular momentum in a axial
ax axially symmetric system the angular
momentum and the angular orientation
would be another one yeah
okay and there are lots of
others usually for
example if you have some
field typically the field and its time
derivative are uh are conjugate
variables so there's all kinds of
uh any the other questions yes what
think it seems like when we went from uh
uh discret states observables with
discret states to continuous there's a
kind of subtle change in representation
in the following s that in that case in
the discreet States The Operators
operated on the ks the wave function was
just an expansion Cod yeah yeah yeah but
we could right but we we could also rep
remember we also represent the operators
as
matrices and the Kats as columns but a
column is just a list of values
of an amplitude as a function of where
it's lying how high you know as a
function of an igen value so it's uh it
really is the same
thing um this is closely related to the
representation of operators as
matricies just a concrete concrete uh
action in a particular basis when you
write column vectors you write them in
particular
basis right
all right last remark last remark about
uncertainty
is the uncertainty
principle for this particular example
here I'm not going to derive the
uncertainty principle not today and we
may get to it but it really is a very
simple thing it is simply the statement
that uh that this that it's a statement
about for year transforms first of all
and it transcends quantum mechanics it's
not only quantum mechanics anytime you
have a pair of quantities which are
related by Foria in uh or transform in
this way it's generally the case that
the
narrower one Foria pair half of the
Foria PA is the broader the other one is
in other words the narrower the range of
P the broader of X will be and vice
versa so I don't want to go into a a
mathematical uh statement about
um about the uncertainty principle here
but whatever it is it really just does
have to do with the character of Foria
uh pairs XMP in this
case we'll come back to it I
think what I wanted to get on
to was the hamiltonians for particles
just the simplest possible hamiltonians
for particles and how they govern the
quantum mechanical
Evolution remember what the hamiltonian
is the hamiltonian is the thing which
first of all enters into the Schrodinger
equation and which also governs the time
evolution of the state Vector the
hamiltonian is to be identified with the
classical idea of energy
just as it is in classical
mechanics if you go back we
I I discussed this earlier but let's uh
let's go on the starting point was the
idea of the unitary evolution of State
vectors that state vectors evolve by
unitary
transformation and then we said well
what happens if you make a tiny little
unit tin tiny little change in time
that's correspond to some sort of
differential change in the state
vector and we found out that that
differential change was governed by a
Herm Mission
operator called the hamiltonian so I if
you um have forgotten the details of
that go back to it now not not right now
but
uh but you'll remember the
equation the equation for the evolution
of a state vector
is
I let's put our H bars in for the moment
take them out again in a little
while
DCI by
DT the way the state Vector we can write
this in terms of State vectors the state
Vector is generally a function of time
the state changes with time you can take
the difference between vectors and you
can differentiate vectors with respect
to time if a vector happens to be time
dependent you can differentiate it I DCI
by
DT is equal to the hamiltonian operator
acting on S that's the time dependent
Schrodinger equation we worked at I
think we worked out an example for a
spin processing in a magnetic field
where we just used for the hamiltonian
one of the components of the
spin here is the general form of the
Schrodinger equation the time dependent
Schrodinger
equation and let's try out some simple
hamiltonians see what kind of things we
learn from them tonight I think we'll
just uh study one or two and then we'll
go on afterwards the very simplest
hamiltonian that I can write down which
is quite illustrative and nobody ever
writes it down but I'm going to write it
down anyway
is H now H is an operator not just an
operator it's a Herm Mission
operator H doesn't stand for Herm
Mission stands for hamiltonian but never
mind
uh I'm going to try H is equal to a
number constant C for constant times the
momentum perfectly good thing let's see
what it does let's see what kind of
thing we learn from it um is this a
reasonable hamiltonian for a particle
yeah actually it is and we'll find out
in a moment what kind of particle but uh
it's not the usual thing what do we
usually write for a non-relativistic
particle p^ s over 2 m huh momentum
squar over twice the mass we'll come
back to that but this is simpler this is
simpler and worth exploring first just
to see how the apparatus works
uh everything here should be capitalized
everything because they're all
operators okay but how how is this
represented in terms of wave functions
in terms of wave functions and we would
wave function s of
X wave functions in the X basis in the
momentum basis wave functions in the X
basis are just projections onto the
exigen vectors and we can do that inside
these equations here it's it's fine um
what this reads then is
i d s of X by
DT this is the way the wave function
changes is
equal now H is C * P so let's put the C
there and P is minus I HR d by
DX so there's a
minus an i an H bar and a d by
DX s of
X okay what have I done I've Rewritten
this
equation in terms of wave functions in
other words a concrete representation s
of x d s of X by DT and I've used here
the assumption that the hamiltonian is
just equal to C * the momentum and the
momentum is i- I HR d by DX
well this is a very and of course s is
not only a function of X what is s a
function of
time it's a function of time because in
general a state Vector changes with time
that's
all okay we can uh let's cancel out the
I
bars and I just get
DCI by DT
is equal to minus C * DCI by
DX
or DCI by
DT plus DCI by DX with a c is equal to
zero that's a pretty simple
equation in fact it's so simple that I
know what not only what a what a
solution is I know all of the solutions
of this
equation anybody know what the solutions
of this equation are the general
solution a function of xus
CT any
function let's let's leave it this
way any function which is a function of
x minus CT
in other words it doesn't depend on x
and t separately it only depends on the
combination x minus CT will solve this
equation if I differentiate with respect
to
T that will be minus c times the
derivative with respect to X and that's
all this equation says any function of
this form will solve the Schrodinger
equation so let's think about a function
of this form what does it do what does
it look like
you can start at t equal
Z cross out T here with any function s
of
X of course we don't want to take any
function uh I want my functions to be
such that the total probability is equal
to one so the integral of s star SI
should be finite equal to one uh they
shouldn't blow up or or they should be
they should fall to zero nicely so that
we can integrate
them but they can do all they can do
whatever you
like some sort of lump that can
oscillate may or may not oscillate um
and rather
General and now we let T run we let time
go forward what happens to this solution
what happens to the solution is it stays
EX exactly the same shape except every
feature of it moves with a velocity C
the features of it move to the
right with uniform velocity
C that's what this function is it's just
a function which just moves rigidly
without changing its shape and of course
it's a complex function so it has a real
part and an imaginary part but both of
them maintain exactly the same shape and
they just slide down the axis uniformly
with a velocity
C now I chose C for a
reason because it's a speed of
light is this a photon well this is not
really the correct description of
photons but it's pretty close to the
right description of neutrinos at least
neutrinos which move with a speed of
light
real neutrinos probably move a little
slower than the speed of light but
unmeasurably
so so this would be a darn good
description of one dimensional
neutrinos except that we would have to
add another possibility that they can
all these were all these are pure Right
Moving
neutrinos they're pure Right Moving the
tunos and they do have a funny thing
that the energy can be we're going to
come back to this not not this quarter I
think but the energy can be both
positive and negative p is a thing which
can be positive or
negative so this particle has the
property that it can have positive or
negative energy but that's not import
what's important here is the picture of
the wave function moving down the axis
with uniform velocity the whole
probability distribution rigidly moves
down the axis what happens to the
expectation value of x
it moves the same way so the expectation
value of x moves with velocity
CT and um that's the quantum mechanics
of the simple system I would just point
out that if we compare this with the
classical mechanics of exactly the same
system hamiltonian is equal to
CP how do we compare the uh how do we do
the classical physics
we use Hamilton's
equations so here it was mainly for this
reason right here that we did all
quarter of of classical mechanics last
quarter so that well not just for this
one but for all sorts of things like
this um Hamilton's equations let's look
at Hamilton's equations Hamilton's
equations are
DH by
DP equals x dot
and d h by
DX equal minus P
dot d h by DT is just equal to C
right the H by thex that's equal to
zero so what this says classically is
that the momentum is conserved now we'll
come back to the conservation of
momentum in quantum
mechanics but it also says that the
position of the particle moves with
velocity
C in quantum mechanics the whole
probability distribution in this case
this is a very very simple case sort of
engineered just to have a simple answer
the whole probability distribution moves
with uh but in particular the
expectation value of x moves with
velocity C so the expectation value of
the position behaves according to the
classical equations of
motion now that's that's this as I said
this is a very easy
example um which is
uh a little too simple to be perfectly
General but
uh but it does illustrate the
uh so this would be the Schrodinger
equation for this very very simple
hamilt I
okay I think we're about uh all right
let's go a little more little
more what about a and of course this
would make this a relativistic particle
this would not be a non-relativistic
particle is a guy who moves with the
speed of light
okay yeah I mean without using the C
just using some other number ver speed
of light you know um would this be the
the correct hamiltonian for any particle
moving in free space no any particle
which is always constrained to move with
the same velocity so right right so for
example
um you know just as
photons are the Quant of the
electromagnetic
field sound waves and crystals also have
quanta and those sound waves are called
phon
and at least at low energies those
phonons move with a uniform velocity the
uniform velocity being the speed of
sound so if you had one-dimensional
phonons you would describe them in a
similar way could just do that would you
just throw an electron in free space and
it wouldn't follow
that
uh no electrons don't generally move
with a speed of light I'm just saying at
any speed or no no no no you see
this this law of physics for this
particular kind of particle says that no
matter how you throw it with whatever
momentum you throw it with it's always
going to move the same
way right he said replace the C with the
V with a what he said replace the C with
with velocity V but velocity V means
momentum but PB is the same as p^2 2 not
quite it's p p uh it's p s M but that's
close to the that right that's close
right imagining that any of one thing
for a relativistic particle of course p
is not V over M but you're on the right
track yeah I was just imagine that any
particle has a has a wave function for
its position right and if it's moving in
space that would that wave function is
just moving no no no no you see that's
that's that's not quite right
um only for this very very simple
situation does the wave function move
with this rigid behavior and maintain
its
shape not true more generally if you
take a non-relativistic electron we're
going to work out its equation in two
minutes uh the shape of its wave
function is not maintained it sort of
wobbles and does things and sort of
gradually falls apart and disperses
uh diffuses disperses whatever you want
to call it
so
um right as I picked this one just
because it's easy to solve but um but it
doesn't
represent uh the most General kind of
motion of a particle all right so let's
let's talk about let's take a guess
let's take a guess for a
non-relativistic
particle um I think I already earlier
showed you that the equations of motion
for expectation
values CL uh Quantum mechanically are
very closely related to the
corresponding equations of motion
classically Hamilton's equations or Pome
Pome bracket form of
them
um so you can imagine that if you want
to represent the quantum mechanics of a
system
which is uh which whose classical
physics you know you basically use the
same
hamiltonian now we will come back to
that we'll come back to that and justify
it better but the natural hamiltonian to
guess for a non-relativistic particle is
just a good old p^ squ over 2 m this is
not a particle with a force on it this
is a particle with no force on it a free
particle the energy the kinetic energy t
is equal to 12 Mass * velocity squared
momentum is M * V and we can rewrite the
kinetic energy if that's all there is
let's call it h as p^2 over 2
m so that's the hamiltonian for a
classical
particle notice this hamiltonian has a
funny feature particles can only move to
the right there are no there's no left
moving motion
they all only move to the
right
uh and that's a funny
thing the asymmetry between left and
right has to do with the fact that p
goes to minus P when you invert left and
right the hamiltonian changes sign when
you this this hamiltonian when you that
that's a funny thing you would the
energy of a particle with negative
momentum is negative energy of a
particle with positive momentum is
positive that's a little bit weird okay
uh non ordinary non-relativistic
particle its energy is independent of
which way it's moving and that's ensured
by the fact that the energy is
proportional to p^ squ not
P right so let's start with the energy
being p^2 over 2m and work out the
Schrodinger equation for it now we will
work be working out the genuine
Schrodinger well the original version of
the Schrodinger equation for free
particle we just write H is equal to p^2
over 2 m h is also I D by
DT now let's put H bar in just to
to as Schrodinger would have done
it on
S that's the left hand side thought of
as an operator operating on an equ on a
uh or sorry that's i h Bar D by DT and
the right hand the right hand side of
the equation is just H acting on side
but H is p^2 over 2 m so let's write
that there's a 1 over 2
m and then what is p whatever p is we
have to square it but let's write down
what p is first minus HR I
I derivative with respect to X
but we have to square it it's p^ s
squaring it just means multiplying it by
itself so let's Square this I bar
squared and then the square of the first
derivative is the second
derivative mean you just apply it twice
Time s
or on S of
X that's it that's a Stringer equation
for a um ordinary non-relativistic
particle moving on a one-dimensional
line uh let's let's leave the H bars I
bar DCI by
DT is equal to
minus H bar squar the minus comes from
minus i^
2 over 2 m
dcai by dx^
2 this is a kind of wave equation
incidentally this is also a wave
equation this is a wave equation and S
is a wave function this is a wave
equation s is also a wave function this
is the shinger equation for for an
ordinary non-relativistic
particle it has the property that waves
of different wavelength move with
different velocity I'm getting a little
tired so I we're going to quit soon but
um waves of
different
uh wavelength move with different
velocities because of that the wave
function does not maintain its
shape and in fact it tends to fall apart
and uh and
um
uh spread okay the wave function spreads
out with time unlike this very simple
case over here in this case no matter
what the wavelength no matter what the
momentum is they all move with the same
velocity not so here different momentum
move with different
velocities and so a wave with a given
shape different parts of it will move
with different velocity different uh
wavelength different wavelengths in it
will move with different velocities and
it will sort of fall apart uh we'll
study it a little in more detail and
we'll study Its Behavior but um I think
I'm for more please visit us at
stanford.edu